Guide to the Emma Goldman Papers, 1909-1941 and undated RL.11353
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters, 1909-1941 and undated; 1
  - Mother Earth Publishing Association (New York, New York) to Freedom Press (London, England), 1915 January 22; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    An unidentified employee orders some books, then comments on the problem of selling books: "Because all the stupid men of Europe are busy killing each other that is no reason why the intelligent men shouldn't be reading." There is an update regarding Alexander Berkman's activities and a comment on Kropotkin's stance on the war.
    Mother Earth Publishing Association; Freedom Press (London, England); Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Kropotkin, Petr Alekseevich, kniaz, 1842-1921
  - Bert G. Plattin to the editor of The Communist (n.p.), [1922] February 2; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Plattin questions why the paper has been silent regarding the "vendetta of the ruling class in Russia against our comrades the Anarchists & Syndicalists."
    Political persecution -- Soviet Union -- History; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936
  - R. W. Postgate, The Communist (London, England) to Messrs. Platten Randolph, Robert & Konna, The Cooperative Land & Crafts Guild (Holt, England), 1922 February 8; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Postgate writes that he imagines the letters refer to the expulsion of Emma Goldman and Alexander Berkman from Russia. He argues that the two were supported by the Russian government, and in return only attacked the government as "bitterly as they could." The government asked them to move on. He adds "I think you should remember that the present Government in Russia is a dictatorship of the proletariat."
    Political persecution -- Soviet Union -- History; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936; Postgate, Raymond, 1896-1971; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
  - Edward Shortt (n.p.) to Colonel J. C. Wedgwood, M. P. (n.p.), 1922 February 24; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Home Secretary Shortt writes that Max Eastman has sailed from New York and should be refused entry to the country.
    Eastman, Max, 1883-1969
  - Li-Pei-Kan (Shanghai, China) to Dear Comrade [Emma Goldman] (n.p.), 1925 September 20; 3 Leaves; 5 pages; 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Kan writes of conditions in China, the labor movements and activities of the imperialists and the Communist Party, along with his own work at writing anarchist articles and translations.
    China -- Politics and government -- 1912-1949; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Li-Pei-Kan (Shanghai, China) to Dear Comrade [Emma Goldman] (n.p.), 1925 October 31; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Kan discusses the civil war in China and the activities of Communists. He requests literature from Freedom Press.
  - [Illegible] Newman (London, England) to Tom Keell (n.p.), 1928 March 7; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Newman discusses discovering what happened at a meeting [s]he missed, and borrowed books.
    Keell, Thomas H.
  - Unidentified to Albert E. Arent, 1934 February 16; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    The unidentified writer writes regarding arrangements for Emma Goldman to speak at Cornell.
    Cornell University
  - Edward H. Zabuskie to Emma Goldman, 1934 February 18; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Zabuskie writes to invite Emma Goldman to speak at Dana College, if her schedule permits.
    Dana College (Newark, N.J.)
  - Helen Hau[nam] Joseph to Emma Goldman, 1934 February 27; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Joseph offers any help she can provide for Goldman's visit to Cleveland, then invites Goldman to dine with her at her home.
  - [Kochaks?] (Bordighera, Italy) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1934 December 28; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    [Kochaks] thanks Keell for his comments on a book he has written, then describes his return to living in a village in Italy.
  - Unidentified (n.p.) to Emma Goldman (New York, New York), 1910 June 25; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    The writer purchases a subscription for Goldman's book.
  - "One who does not approve" to whom it may concern, undated; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    On the back of a flyer for the event, the writer disapproves of Emma Goldman's speaking about her autobiography in Philadelphia, and expresses surprise at the list of "respected" citizens noted as sponsors.
    Anarchists -- United States
  - R.A.P [Preston] to Mr. [Alfred A.] Knopf, undated; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Preston provides a favorable internal reader's report for Goldman's autobiography.
    Autobiographies; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984
  - Unidentified (n.p.) to editor of L'Adunata dei refrattari (n.p.), undated; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Handwritten letter to the editor or article for this New York City newspaper, regarding stipulations the State Department has placed on Emma Goldman's reentry into the country.
- Papers, 1916-1940 and undated
  The Papers Series includes materials related to various prominent anarchists in addition to Emma Goldman. There are typescript drafts of four articles and letters by anarchists; nine handwritten articles on anarchist themes written in Italian by Errico Malatesta; publications; press releases for Emma Goldman; ephemera, including tickets, brochures, solicitation letters, handbills and flyers; a contract and room layout for speaking engagements by Goldman; Thomas H. Keell's list of works on anarchism; newspaper clippings related to Goldman; and six black-and-white photographs, including one portrait and two group photographs featuring Goldman, one of Alexander Berkman and his girlfriend, one of Harry Kelly, as well as an unidentified subject.
  - Typescript articles and letters, 1922, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes four typescript articles and letters, often with annotations or corrections, signed by the authors, including Alexander Berkman, Emma Goldman, and [Alexander?] Shapiro. Topics include persecution and prisons in Russia and discussion of anarchist theory.
  - Errico Malatesta handwritten articles, 1929 and undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes six articles by Malatesta, written on various anarchist topics.
  - Errico Malatesta handwritten articles, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes three articles by Malatesta, written in Italian on various anarchist topics.
  - Publications, 1930, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes two publications: one related to Alexander Berkman's 60th birthday celebration held at the Central Opera House in New York City (1930); the other to the Modern School of Stelton Twenty-fifth Anniversary (1940).
  - Press releases, 1934 and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes eighteen press releases for Emma Goldman. Some are master copies; the majority probably date to the 1930s.
  - Ephemera, 1924-1937 and undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes invitations, tickets, flyers, and handbills, mostly related to speaking engagements or dinners for Emma Goldman. There is also a subscription list form for a book by Alexander Berkman. One flyer is written in Hebrew or Yiddish.
  - Speaking engagement documents, 1934 and undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Inlcudes a 1934 speaking engagement contract for Emmma Goldman, as well as an undated seating chart for a venue.
  - Keell's typescript list of works on anarchism, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes a one-page, annotated list of anarchist works probably maintained by Thomas Keell.
  - Newspaper clippings (originals), 1916-1936 and undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes 29 articles and letters to the editor, almost entirely from papers in London.
  - Newspaper clippings (photocopies), 1916-1936 and undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes photocopies of the original 29 articles and letters to the editor, almost entirely from papers in London.
  - Photographs, 1930s and undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Includes six gelatin silver and albumen photographs. There is one portrait of Emma Goldman and two group photographs that feature her, a photograph of Harry Kelly, and a photograph of Alexander Berkman and his girlfriend Emmy Eckstein. The final photograph is of an unidentified man.